[Music]
next example this example will help us
again to see better in the
definition let's
consider this funny
surface I hope that from last
week we have learned to visualize this
surface what is this surface called it
had a name by the
way what's this surface
called Hey
[Applause]
huh what is it
called
Dina is it orientable does it have movie
strips no it doesn't have any movie
strips so which one is it it's not n
it's three huh Sigma 3 that's right it's
called Sigma
3 and that's on this Sigma 3 so it's a
Rema surface of Gus 3 you should learn
to say this
quickly let's consider the following
Loops this one which we shall call K
Zer this one which we shall call
K1
and this one
which I which I call l0 and this one
oops which will call L1 is the picture
clear I put a rubber band here rubber
band here rubber band here rubber band
here okay now
question which of those Loops is
isotopic to which one inside Sigma 3
first let's do the easy case uh k0 K1
isotopic inside Sigma
3 who thinks they
are yeah who thinks they are
not what do you
think this whole row didn't vote do you
think k0 and K1 are isotopic to each
other or
not how do you do it it's easy
I take this and then slide it over there
along Sigma
Sigma so you can
say you can be courageous and
declare do isotopic or not k0 and K1
they isotopic so you raise your hand say
yes the isotopic yes it's a very easy
question and I'm a clever for I know the
answer okay so there are of course isic
in K k0 and K1 so let's make sure that
we remember to say inside Sigma 3 okay
but it turns out that l0 and
L1 is trickier do you think l0 and L1
are isotopic inside Sigma 3 who thinks
that they are
isotopic L1 l0 and L1 Adrian thinks the
isotopic okay some people who thinks
that okay also who thinks that they are
not isotopic inside Sigma
3 okay so William thinks that they are
not isotopic what what goes wrong why
can't I take this rubber band and slide
it over to the other
side why when I slide it over can't I
slide it over and put it in this
position why not
you say it gets deformed you need but
it's not clear you you realize that
right if I keep saying oh they are
isotopic and you disagree and they say
you you say they are not isotopic you
not going to convince your opponent by
saying oh they get
deformed do you understand what I'm
saying let's say that I disagree with
you and you want to convince me that you
are right and I'm wrong if you just say
oh they get deformed
you can't win the argument like that can
you you have to say something more
powerful more convincing so why are they
not
hopic
H there will be if you try to isotope
one to the other you all agree a stage
where
the rub band looks like
this you
agree I'd like to ask you at this moment
is the this
Loop inside Sigma
no the loop is not entirely on Sigma 3
on the surface it leaves Sigma 3 do do
you see why there's a hole there and
while it's here it's touching Sigma 3
but then it stops touching Sigma 3 and
it's sort of over this
hole Yeah so it's not inside Sigma 3 at
this stage so we had to we said that in
order to say whether two things are
isotopic or not we have to specify in
what ambient Dimension and here the
ambient space Sigma 3 is not large
enough to move it over who did not
understand please raise your hands and
please be honest it's it's a very very
important Point although it's an easy
point so if you do not understand I want
to make sure that everyone understands
this before we move on who did not
understand that this
stage step is not
allowed yeah because excuse
me
because the L subt goes outside
partly outside Sigma
3 so the answer is that they are not
isotopic inside
Sigma yes you have a
question what do you mean Sigma 4 Sigma
4 is another thing like this I try to
move it from here to here it's still
impossible what's what does Sigma 4 mean
Sigma 4 looks like this right you have
another ho another handle and
I do you agree that that's what Sigma 4
looks
like you don't agree you're confused you
are confused I think I can guess why
you're confused because you keep
thinking ah 3 4
5 you have forgotten what those 3 four
five mean three of what four of what
five of what before we were
discussing 3 4 five
Dimensions here we are saying 3 4 2
number of handles but they all have the
same Dimension is that what we were
confused
about
yes but Sigma 3 does not mean three
diens
iions you say ah but if you look at your
notes the definition of Sigma 3 is the
surface Dimension two always which has
three handles that was a
definition you should not change the
definition between Friday and
Monday even though even though it's
tempting to do so by the way many things
do change over the weekend of course but
not math not mathematical definitions
okay so Sigma 3 is simply means that
there are three handles let's revise
William how do you
call this
surface Sigma 2 correct how do you call
what do you call excuse me this
surface Sigma 3 but it's the same
Dimension it's always two Dimensions
okay
good
however the the problem occurred here
because the rubber band or The
Loop LT left to the surface was sort of
hanging in mid a of
course if we do the isotopy in a larger
space for example inside R3 this whole
thing let's say is inside
R3 which you imagine then they become
isotopic of course in fact they become
toic in the following way as well I can
make this very large yeah that's okay I
can leave the surface because I have R3
to move stuff in and then move and then
shr so there I stoping R3 but not on
Sigma 3 not on the surface outside yes
which illustrates once again the idea
that you have to specify the
ambient di in which you are trying to
since we are beginning to become experts
in this a tricky
example which I'd like to
give not as a project because I think
it's a little too small to be a project
okay let's give it as a project because
I like easy projects okay so this is a
project I'm going to add this project to
the list of projects and ask Yan to put
them share with you and so on okay and
so you can do this for next week if you
like and it's relatively
straightforward a tricky
example let us
consider this strip
do you see what I have just drawn it is
a movie
strip with two
twists
now if I start sliding my hand on this
side
here I go in the
back and then after one more twist I go
in front and then I go all the
way in the rare and come back so this
surface has two sides it's not like a
movie strip which is one side it has two
sides it's
orientable so
topologically it
is just a copy of this ordinary St not
twists zero
twist okay so these are
homeomorphic I hope you
agree
[Applause]
homeomorphic same topological object
now the question
is are
they
isotopic in
R3 in other words can you make this from
a sheet of
paper or sheet of rubber if you like and
by twisting and so on but never tearing
it cutting it so bring it into this
shape who thinks you can who thinks this
is isotopic to this in R3 raise your
hands who thinks that they are not
isotopic to each other in
R3 I hope everyone thinks so and of
course they are not stoping answer is
no
in
RM
for M 4 5 6 7 Etc so in what dimension
do they become isotopic or do they ever
are they always not
isotopic do you understand the question
okay I'm going to write it down so is
there does there
exist exist some
M for
which they are they become
isotopic in other words you can deform
one to the other without any self
intersection without any cheating in
RM if the answer is yes please give me
the minimum n yeah from M onwards this m
onwards maybe it's 10 maybe it's 20
maybe it's 20045 and so on if there is
no such M please tell me why there's no
such M that's the
project
It's Tricky but it's doable with the
knowledge that you have at hand
okay okay so
that's nice
enough in the first week
and for most of today we have been
discussing the following topics in
topology first we began with lots and
lots of examples of manifolds you know
surfaces and projective plan and all
that kind of thing and we learned to
slide handles we understood more less we
did not prove it but we understood the
classification theorem for all surfaces
so in dimension two we are done those
were that those supplied us with a stock
of examples many many examples and
instantly many pictures which was the
most important thing in this course
please keep drawing pictures and then we
discussed the concept of moving things
around we formalized the concept of
deformation isotopy we call it inside
somean Space now we shall start
discussing a new chapter and that's
topological invariance using the concept
of isotopy we shall now produce
something like energy you know when a
physical system even evolves after some
experiment something happens the rain
falls on it she kicks the machine and so
on before and after the energy is the
same that's called the conservation of
energy and sometimes using the
conservation energy you can draw with
draw lots of interesting conclusions
about physics it's similar we shall
introduce a
concept called the intersection number
and that intersection number this
interesting thing is conserved in the in
the course of
deformations so chapter
three some people call it intersection
index but because the plural of indexes
is indices and plural of number is
numbers I think number is an easier
word
okay we'll start ing
intersections with not just oh those two
things
intersecting Five Points we'll start
counting them with plus or minus sign
you will say ah this
intersection happens but it has plus
sign this intersection minus sign and so
we will start
counting intersections or Crossings if
you like
with
signs in other words with plus or minus
so some intersections will be counted
minus and some things with
plus consider two curves inside let's
say the
plane let's say that these curves look
like this K and L okay in R2 so think of
the black border as R2 and there are two
curves like this and these curves keep
going but let's not worry about where
they go let's focus on what happens in
this under this
microscope okay intersecting at let's
call this point
P choose also an orientation
orientation for the ambient
R2 for example do you know this
abbreviation eg it means for example in
in Latin is Exemplar
genis let's say that this is our
orientation you remember the exercises
that we did on Friday that's the
orientation okay yeah now
and we shall choose
orientations for K and
L having chosen those orientations the
sign of
p is now let's consider four cases
because there are four cases this this
is K this is L
oops I'm drawing the same picture they
may not look like the same but please
forgive me they are the
same
um l
k
okay and that's the point p in each of
the pictures the orientation for the
ambient R2 is is always this okay the
standard orientation if you let's say
that in this picture bless you bless you
twice who who sneeze
twice who who was that ah very good
okay okay so let's say that K is
oriented like this L is oriented like
this okay
L okay let me rewrite this I'm sorry I
would like to be a little more precise
so the
sign of the intersection K intersect L
which is
p yeah is so I'm being a little
imprecise I'm sorry but we are taking K
and L in this order K first L second
okay so let me show you what I mean k
first L second so that's one and that's
two if you like FS1 and FS2 do you think
this orientation is the same orientation
as the ambient orientation or
opposite it's the same okay you've been
well trained so this is plus we say that
this intersection is plus what about
this oops oh why am I doing this this
exactly the same
picture you see you should have told me
that I'm doing something
CD I want to do this and want to do this
of course yeah oops and then
this that's more interesting
hey that's plus how about this that's
one that's two negative okay we are all
together how about
this are we sure it's negative I wish
that's one that's two
who thinks it's
negative who thinks it's
positive who thinks it's something
else one two if I turn it around it's
one two is it the same as this it's the
opposite it's negative thank you very
much and that of course is positive it's
some much tricky but it's one two now
and when I turn it around it's the same
orientation as the ambiental so you now
see what we mean by sign I hope yeah
okay so this is with respect to the
ambient operation and of course we if we
had chosen the opposite ambient
orientation for R2 all the signs would
be reversed so if we had
chosen tricky tense Construction in
English if we had chosen um the opposite
orientation E1 and E2 like this
for R R2
instead
then the signs all the
signs would have been
opposite plus would have become minus
minus would have become
plus no problem I hope opposite okay
[Applause]
here what about the
case
about degenerate
cases like this let's say
that K is like this and L is like this
and they are like
that K and
L and if you put Say Arrow here Arrow
here do you think this is positive or
negative we can't
tell the tangent vectors
here so this is K this is L and I'm
going to use color excuse me to do
the
see so that's tangent K that's tangent
to L yeah tangent Vector are
parallel or lineally
dependent so we cannot
decide plus or minus ah thank you very
much
yeah it's difficult to see it under
reflection yeah so we cannot decide
whether plus or minus okay but what do
you do in mathematics when you have a
degeneracy like this what do you do with
de and you know this kind of picture if
you think about it is a very very
exceptional very perverse picture for
example you cannot draw this picture on
the moving
train if you want on the moving train
it's
going and you try to do this oops and
then you
this yeah
or you cannot draw this picture on the
moving
train yeah so pictures that you cannot
draw on the moving train are bad
pictures good pictures you should be
able to draw on the moving
train
so but
let us
deform the Dig case
to
generic generic means something that you
can draw in a moving train
situations
C2
a yeah very
important this
and what you get is as
follows this
becomes
either this or
this if you shake a little
bit okay now let's say that here I'm
introducing the orientation like this
here I'm introducing orientation like
this let's do the bottom one first how
many intersections are there no
intersection has disappeared so here you
get zero intersection you don't have
plus or
minus
here let's see those two intersection
there are two intersections now what
let's keep the
same
orientation ambient orientation like
this so this is with respect to I'm
sorry I'm coming to this corner of the
picture and it's difficult to see I I
know especially for people with bad eyes
set like myself but let's say this is a
orientation standard one is this
intersection positive or
negative K like this L like this yeah
one and two hey can you see for example
ham can you see from all the way back
you have very good eyes don't here so
this intersection where K is moving like
this and L is moving like this is this
positive or negative with respect to the
standard orientation positive thank you
so this is positive that one is negative
yeah so in fact this intersection is one
+ one minus one again it's
zero so you
see I perturbed it I shook the picture I
deformed it into generic situations in
different ways but the total is always
the same and this is what allows us to
define the in introduced
invariant
okay let me mention one more
example so what we have just said is
that will you
[Applause]
get the same
of
signs
independently
independ toy of how we
default okay French speakers among you
please be careful independent in English
e in French is
independ a but in English it's e here
okay you don't say independent
dly how Okay
likewise in a similar
fashion let's consider
another degenerate case let's say that
you have K which is horizontal if you
like and L which is like the cubic curve
y = x Cub if you like yeah so L comes
from here and goes through and K goes
straight through what is the sign of
this intersection with respect to the
orientation that we're always taking so
one and two we cannot tell because it's
degenerate okay so let's shake
it there are two ways to
shake keep K like this but think of L as
a
string all right and then tighten the
string a little bit Boop and then what
you get is going to be something like
this H that's L that's
L that's K so this
is tighten the
string like this if you pull this end of
this end a little bit you get before
there were tangent now I have a nonzero
angle here
another way to deform this into
generousity is you loosen it you push a
little bit here and here can you see
push a little bit and as a result what
do you get you get something like
this yeah that's
loosening okay let's see what kind of
intersection numbers we
get is this intersection now we have one
single generic intersection is the sign
positive or
negative yeah it's positive it's easy
see how about here we have now three
intersections that appeared out of
this this
intersection is positive it looks the
same as this picture this one negative
indeed K goes that way L goes that way
so it's one two that's negative of
disorientation so that's negative and
finally it's easy to check this is
positive so so here we get just + one
here get + one -1 + 1 = again + one it's
the same
thing okay so it always
works okay and the point is that both of
these are generic
pictures generic
situations okay I shall State one um
definition and then we'll leave it at
that
okay now the mystery of the Eraser ah
they all converged here maybe all the
erasers end up on this black Bo
eventually
interesting I wonder where erasers go
home to sleep maybe over
there looks a bit like Kung Fu
[Music]
no
okay precise
definition let's say that you have two
sub manifolds inside an ambient manifold
M be such
that first of all I'm going to say they
have exactly the right
um overflow so they intersect in
points like that the Overflow was
dimensional K plus dimensional L minus
dimensional M as you recall but equal in
other words the Overflow is exactly
zero overflow zero means
that from
Friday that was chapter 2 the one I
think yeah that's right um K and L
generically intersecting
points set in discrete points let me
even say that so you can count those
intersections 1 2 3 4 5 to each of those
discrete intersection points we direct a
sign a plus or minus I how do you do
this if they do
assume
that that at all intersection
points at all these intersection
points K and L are not
tangent in other words
not a situation like this but a
situation like this or not a situation
like this but rather situations like
this okay so if you like you can also
think of it as follows if that
is if um that they make nonzero angles
that's maybe more
intuitive so they intersect but at
nonzero angles
okay so assume this then we
say that K and
L are
transversal strange word have you ever
met this word before transversal
transver transverse and so on they cut
each other nicely that's what they mean
in
m and we shall
write K and L intersect e m but in order
to show that they intersect nicely we're
going to put this strange
sign that's the symbol for saying that K
and L intersect in discrete points and
at all those intersection points the
angle intersection is non zero that they
are not t so here they are not
transverse transversal but here they are
transversal
okay okay by the way this might be a S
letter in Amar or something like this
what is this is no it's not okay well
it's not thing
I'm okay and I'd like to show you a
number of examples
to see if we understand what transversal
means so these are the transversal
examples and then in a moment non
transversal examples let's say that K is
like this and suppose that L comes in
and Rises like this just cuts through
not straight up but almost this is
transversal K and are
transversal and similarly if you have K
like this and L comes
up and Rises and then plunges
down goes down and then rises again
that's
transversal okay so that's transversal
transversal in
[Applause]
contrast in
contrast I need it to erase
not transversal
pictures you can invent those pictures
yourselves of course you can have K like
this and if you imagine that L comes up
but you see as it approaches K imagine
that it becomes tangent to K and then
goes like this like the cubic curve that
we discussed that's not transversal the
angle at the at the point of
intersection is zero another interesting
example of non transversality is as
follows suppose that in analogy with the
top picture I come up but then I come
down I don't deep down I just touch K
and then I leave I take off
again this picture is not transversal
because this intersection point is fine
but this at this
point those to sub for the
tangent so that picture is not
transversal do you understand that
transversality is a severe expensive
condition you have to have nonzero angle
everywhere even if the condition fails
at one point bank that disqualifies you
from being transversal okay and finally
transversality is a
robust resue
stable
nice generic condition all the
adjectives
condition namely what what do I
mean okay that if K and L are
transversal in
M then if you perturb them slightly if
you shake the picture a little bit if
you deform the station a little bit
small
perturbations keep the transversality
whereas if they're not
transversal to begin
with then a small peration will make
them transversal as for example it
happened here and L were not transversal
at this point but if I shook a little
bit it became transversal any other way
will make it transversal so small
pensions make
so you can see that the transversality
is a more General condition nicer
condition robust stable
condition
okay tomorrow we shall see many
interesting applications of
transversality we have to finish today
by defining transversality and not
officially defining how you count the
intersection number that's how we shall
start next next time okay